Welcome to the TRT and Hormone
Optimization YouTube channel and we have
a new guest today. That's Mason Collins.
Welcome, Mason.
>> Thanks for having me. Big fan. I've been
watching your stuff for a long time. So,
I'm uh appreciate the opportunity to be
here.
>> Very welcome. So, maybe start by
introducing yourself to the viewers.
>> Sure. I'm Mason Collins. Uh we have a
clinic in Texas uh live oak testosterone
and weight loss where we primarily do
men and women hormone optimization uh
weight loss. We have an aesthetic side
as well but our bread and butter is
going to be um hormone optimization and
then we sprinkle weight loss metabolic
uh health in there as well.
>> Why exactly did you become so interested
in HRT and TRT? Yeah, it started I was
just men's health only um a couple years
ago. I've been doing it for a little
over three and a half years and uh I was
men's health only and then it kind of
branched into the GLP1 started becoming
a little bit more popular and I started
using them uh for my the guy patients I
had their wives I had them on GLP1s
they're doing really well and then I
kind of got to where I really wanted
some I was missing a piece and that was
really the female hormone optimization
part and so we kind of started doing a
lot of female hormone training and
education and learning a lot by that. So
he implemented that. Um and so just kind
of to overall take care of you know
couples and the entire person as a
female not just focus on weight loss but
to where it all started from. Uh
[clears throat]
my main background is emergency
medicine. So I was in the emergency
department for about 10 years. And you
know, it's funny. I talk with a lot of
clinic owners and people in the space
and a lot of them seem to move from the
emergency department to this and so I
don't know if it just naturally
gravitates to where you know in the
emergency department you see them 10
years after they needed to make changes
and you know and so now I'm hoping to
I'm hoping to prevent that ER visit in
10 years whether it's from a heart
attack a broken hip you know hormones
have incredible
uh health and metabolic parameters that
help keep people's hearts healthy, keeps
their bones healthy. And so I think it
mainly just came to be I just didn't
want to be the sickly, frail patient in
the ER that I was having to take care
of. And so I think that's kind of how it
really stemmed. And now it's just
awesome keeping happy people h happy,
healthy, and as optimal as possible.
>> Awesome. What are your typical uh
clients like? Um are they overweight?
Are they already 40 45 and older? Or are
they ver diverse population?
>> Yeah, we kind of see a mixture of
everybody. I um really whenever I
started as men's health only I thought
my population was really going to be
about 50 to 70 um because I was mainly
focusing on testosterone and um I wasn't
really expecting to see the amount of
low testosterone guys as I see and even
once we started taking care of women and
everything they have kind of hormonal
derangement earlier and earlier as well.
So I would say typically probably 30 to
70. Um and then women we do do a lot of
post-menopause uh hormone optimization
as well. So they're kind of older. Guys
of course have I mean just any age can
really benefit from testosterone. The
younger ones are the harder ones to
manage to to you know just right off the
bat um in terms of their fertility. and
if they're a female of childbearing age,
make sure we're not doing anything that
could harm a a baby. But, um, for the
most part, our population clientele is,
I mean, across all ages,
>> right? I can tell from the views, uh, on
the videos we make that a lot of men
especially are interested in TRT
add-ons. So, what can we do extra on top
of our TRT to feel even better, to
optimize our health even better? Uh
maybe to lose weight or uh to um to make
sure we we live a qualitative uh
lifestyle. Um so, you're also doing
peptides. Uh you you told me. Yep.
>> Yeah. So, I'll I'll give kind of the
unsexy answer at first, you know, first
I really want people, you know, to do
the lifestyle stuff first. I know that's
boring, you know, just kind of get a
sigh like, "No, I just want to hear the
cool stuff." But if you're not, you
know, prioritizing your sleep, if you
don't have a good exercise regimen, if
you're not watching, you know, your
nutrition, you know, eat like an adult
and, you know, you're not in control
your mental health and, you know, your
hormones prior to peptides and
everything are out of out of whack,
you're just not going to get much out of
them. So, we kind of first want to
address the lifestyle things. Um, and
then of course with guys, testosterone
fixes a lot of the stuff, the low
energy, drive, motivation, clears up
brain fog, helps libido, helps improve
muscle gain, muscle recovery, all that
stuff. Um, and it all the other
lifestyle factors only get more out of
it. But on top of that, say we do have a
decent testosterone level, they are
working on their lifestyle, you know,
add-ons first. I'll throw in thyroid,
make sure, you know, vitamin D, that
kind of stuff is good as well. And then
say they are pulling all the big levers,
you know, they're sleeping well, they're
working out four or five days a week and
they just kind of looking for an extra
edge, then I do I will bring on uh
peptides. And I mean, we just had the
conversation before, you know, the
peptides from a legitimate compounding
pharmacy can get uh pretty expensive
pretty quick. So, I don't want them to
be wasting their money and feel that
they're not getting much out of them.
So, we just kind of have the
conversation, you know, if you don't
have a good workout regimen, if you're
not sleeping and trying to recover
appropriately, you're not hitting your
nutrition goals. And I just I don't want
them to be bad at me because they're not
getting what they wanted out of them.
But there are a few that have good
results. I mean, the main ones that I
use for Morland, CJC1295, Ipamorland,
um, Tessa Morlin are probably the top
ones that I use. I like Tessa Morlin
one. It has great visceral fat
mobilization and it actually has a lot
of human studies. You know, there are
tons of peptides these days and they're
all pretty good, but really the uh Tesla
Morland Sur Morlin have FDA equivalents
and so they have human data for us to
kind of base off treatments and see what
people have done good and bad. And so
those are the main ones that I do.
Tesmor typically helps visceral fat the
most. CJC1295 and epomorlin the combo
works really well and kind of touching
all of the benefits. Um and then sir
Morland's I would say kind of the daily
driver in a sense it's mild across the
board helps kind of across the board but
um typically more fat loss with
tessammor typically a little better
sleep muscle recovery with CJC1295
and I'll say the top two benefits are
going to be sleep and muscle recovery
and those are the ones that you'll see a
little faster um there are benefits
especially muscle building and fat loss
But they got to be doing the big li uh
levers to make sure they're maximizing
those. And that's going to be with
continued use and, you know, decent
training regimen, decent nutrition. And
that's where they'll really get the
benefits of the extra fat loss and extra
muscle building. But nobody's going to
get huge muscle gains just off peptides
alone, especially if they're not eating,
especially if they don't sleep. They're
just not going to get the benefits that
they're wanting to. I mean, social media
hypes them up like they're just amazing
and they are really cool and they're
good, but they're kind of uh more
truthfully on the the tail end. I want I
want all the other lifestyle metrics in
place. I want testosterone, thyroid, um
those kind of being optimized and worked
on if they're not. And then we bring in
the the peptides for the performance and
everything. And they do have a better
sense of well-being. you do feel a
little better on them dayto-day. And
then with continued use, you can kind of
get some of the anti-aging benefits, the
hair, skin, and nails and everything.
So, they do have a use. I just want to
make sure we're hitting all the big
levers prior to really bringing them on.
>> Yeah. Sure thing. So, those um GH
secrets um do you give them a kind of um
cycle for a certain amount of time? Um,
do you have to post them and restart or
is that just continuously for life?
>> Yeah, and I I kind of let it just how
people want to use them in a sense like
Ega is the brand name of Tesmoron and
that's two grams every night and those
patients that are actually using it for
HIV lipodistrophe do fine. And um
uh but for the most part I'm kind of
with the traditional peptide world on
the five on two off and then um and they
even then they say with that you can use
continuously for the most part if
they're doing it six months in a row
just say hey chill a month and we'll
bring it back. Um I do like them at
night. I do like them 60 minutes after
their last calorie intake uh just to get
the best out of them. I mean, you're
still going to get some benefit if
you're not 100% fasted, but just that
little bit of ghrein release is going to
get a little bit more of a a GH pulse
overnight. And that's kind of how
they're working is they're just getting
your pituitary to pulse growth hormone a
couple more times. And I like that. And
I and it they still allow for the
smatastatin break, meaning they just
don't allow for unregulated growth
hormone to
>> go throughout the body. they have kind
of somatastatin to where it's still
going to keep you within physiologic
parameters, but you can maximize it. You
know, essentially
>> if you only pulse growth hormone one to
three times a night, these can help you
get three to five or six or wherever you
were back in your more youthful years.
And so, um, [clears throat] really to
answer the question, I'm a typical five
five days on or five nights on, two days
off, and then for six months, and then a
month off or so. But the typical dose
for a TRT user is not two grams every
evening, isn't it?
>> You know, I've had a success just doing
500 mics or a gram uh nightly and two
grams seems like or 2 milligrams seems
like a lot. Um, but they do it and they
don't have any incidence of, you know,
cancer and that kind of stuff. And so
that's something I was looking into a
lot and you know it's like okay if we're
improving growth hormone are we going to
be potentially worsening growth hormone
dependent cancers and it seems like it
you know it just improves overall you
know hormonal malu and so you just uh
function better and we still get make
sure they're getting their appropriate
cancer screenings you know colonoscopies
PSAs um papsmears etc and making sure
they're up to date on all that um
[clears throat] but I'm not seeing it
you know pop up cancers and even guys
with like acromegaly or the pituitary
tumors that secrete growth hormone their
entire life you know they will get a
little bit more but even guys I mean
luckily bodybuilders have a skewed data
set to where they use high doses
continuously and they're not dropping
dead of cancers and stuff so
>> exactly
>> they seem very safe
>> do you use any other supplements or
add-ons for sleep especially uh like uh
melatonin.
>> Yeah. Um sleep is something that uh
comes up about with every guy. You know,
some sleep really well, but uh yeah, I
like melatonin. Even high dose
melatonin, I'm not scared of 10 20
milligrams. I like the sustained release
if uh you get it from a compounding
pharmacy. Other ones, I mean, good old
magnesium is probably my favorite
though. Magnesium glycinate andor
thrienate. Um, it helps with sleep
latency, helps induce deep sleep. Adding
some glycine in there may help. 5HT, GA,
5HTP, and GABA has a little bit of use.
Um, I'm not opposed to prescription
trazadone as it's non-habit forming and
continues to allow appropriate sleep
architecture
if they need just because I think sleep
is so important in these guys and it's
our first thing that can be you know
quote unquote slept on you know with our
busy lives and everything um it's easy
to just be like ah I'm only going to do
five to six hours because I feel good
enough to get through it whenever
they're they are sacrificing if it is
body composition you know, muscle
building, muscle recovery. Um, that's
sleep is when muscle you gain your
muscle. That's when you recover. That's
when you form memory. So, we want to try
and maximize as much sleep, quality
sleep as we can get.
>> Mhm. What are the typical symptoms that
are hardest to tackle with testosterone
or TRT? Um, what are some things uh even
if all levels are optimized men still
struggle with? Is that libido or um yeah
difficult uh lack of energy of
difficulties sleeping still?
>> Yep. I would say the top two would be
energy and libido. You know, it's like
we get a guy up and uh they still have
uh their their testosterone levels are
good, right where I want them. I, you
know, consider them optimal that they're
in their compliance and they their
libido is still not where they want it
to be. And libido is so multiffactorial
that it is tough to chase and especially
if they're chasing a libido. And one of
the things you got to ask is like I mean
what are your expectations? Where do you
want to get to? You know and if if it's
unreasonable then it's like you know
you're a working adult you know like
it's hard to want to force you know
extra sessions in a week if you're if
you're wanting to go twice a day or you
know something that like that. But, you
know, if you're just trying to get back
to what you think is healthy for you and
your partner and you're not there, then
uh then we do kind of a deeper dive and
like how much alcohol are you drinking?
Are you getting your sleep in? Is there
relationship turmoil? Um is work or kids
uh causing a lot of stress? Do you have
time to even have intercourse? if you,
you know, everybody is so busy these
days, you know, you have to plan it, you
know, some people you do have to plan
it, you know, and so is that what's
holding you back? And then in terms of
energy, it's kind of the same thing. Um,
a lot of times libido is going to fall
energy, you know, because if your stress
is managed and you feel good and
everything, then yeah, you're going to
have a higher libido and hopefully
energy follows. But energy is kind of
the same. Uh on the caveat that
sometimes I'll be able to add in thyroid
optimization. Um sometimes even just a
little DHEA if their levels are low and
they have other um symptoms that may be
consistent with low DHEA. Sometimes
adding that can kind of fill the gap
that it's typically not super profound
that I found, you know, but I do think
it touch helps touch a little bit in
terms of both energy, libido, and brain
fog. Um especially if their levels are
low or on the lower end.
Do you also look into optimizing DHEA
and pregnnolone in all men?
>> Yeah, and we follow in women too. Um,
and mainly DHEA pregnant I I haven't
found a good lab test that's cost
effective enough. And so I'll bring it
in and get them to trial it. Especially
in guys or gals that are like um,
you know, PTSD, military, first
responders, that kind of stuff. they may
really benefit from it. In guys, the
pregnenolone turns into alopregenolone
and it does in females too, but females
seem to get a better response from
progesterone. But um the pregnalone to
alopregnolone guys can get a lot of the
same benefits that progesterone does in
women in terms of like the calming, the
relaxing, helps with anxiety the next
day, maybe improves sleep. And um just
the lab tests that I've tried to follow
on a couple, I just it's expensive and I
just don't think it's very well. So um I
haven't gotten a a good cost-effective
way to follow pregnenolone like I do
DHEA sulfate levels.
>> What's your typical list of supplements
you recommend to all men and women?
>> Yeah, and supplements are kind of like
at the end of the thing as well. I want
to really do lifestyle then hormone
optimization and then supplements to
fill in the gaps where we need. I do
think highdose fish oil plays a good
role in just kind of brain health, joint
health, total body inflammation. I think
men and women both do well with
creatine. So I like creatine in the
majority of my patients. Um, magnesium.
Most everybody is low and it's hard to
get good magnesium in a diet. So, I do
think mag glycinate, mag 3inate, those
are my favorite. Uh, if I take take them
at night, I dream. I have cool dreams at
night. And so, I enjoy taking at night.
Relaxes me. Gets a little deeper sleep.
Um, and then protein supplementation as
well to make sure they're getting close
to one gram per pound of goal body
weight is
and that and I most people are vitamin D
deficient and so we'll follow that on
the lab if they are. But I try not to
just hand a grab bag of supplements
really. I want to just make sure we can
get lifestyle under control,
hormone optimization where it is and
then fill in the gaps with supplements
if needed.
>> Sure. All right. So maybe let's switch
uh to the women for a moment because for
me personally I think that's even more
difficult area the HRT and women because
we have the progesterone and the
estrogen next to the testosterone DHEA
pregnant it's a difficult mix they have
their periods and pregnancies and
menopause. So um that's a a difficult
thing even for me. Uh I still struggle
listening to patients uh talking about
their minoposal um yeah symptoms and uh
what what the gynecologist recommends
them what the GP recommends them is
still different from what the
endocrinologist will tell them. So uh
what what what's your standpoint in
general on HRT for uh women? Yeah, I
mean women are magical creatures for
sure. Um, but overall the medical
community has just done such a
disservice to women, especially since
the WHI, the Women's Health Initiative,
it made it to where it was scary for
everybody to want to recommend even HRT
to women at all. And so, you know, for
20 years, it's been heavily scrutinized
to where nobody wants to do it. If you
think you're going to do it, then you're
going to have strokes and uh breast
cancer and you need to get off of it as
quick as you can. However, I mean, if
you're backing up and you go to the
Women's Health Initiative and they use
conjugated ecoin estrogen and hydroxy
progesterone acetate, that's not what we
use in hormone uh optimization for
women. We [clears throat] use the
biioidentical estradiol micronized
progesterone. And whenever you're and I
they spent a billion dollars on that
study [clears throat] and use these
compounds that are synthetic and they're
just not even what we make in our own.
They're not the biioidentical onquins.
And so I wish we could undo it and go
back and use estradile and micronized
progesterone but I think that's what
they had most available at the time.
Anyways,
uh disservice to millions of women. And
whenever you use bioidentical estradiol
and micronias progesterone, they have
amazing results without the increase in
breast cancer. They get better
cardiovascular protection from the
estradiol. Their bone health improves,
you know, with the micronized
progesterone. They sleep much better.
Their anxiety is better controlled. You
know, their cycles regulate and if
they're still cycling. But menopausal,
it's easy because they don't have
anything. And so, you know, 50% of the
population is going to go through
menopause and 100% of women will if they
live long enough. And so, this is
something that affects everybody, men
and women both. And I mean, most of the
divorce rate starts about 40 whenever
women are starting to go through per
menopause. I think it's crucial to the
population at as a whole to um get this
get these on board early and follow
women and try and keep them um as happy
and healthy as possible. And it also
limits all the negative stuff
post-menopausal later that can happen.
So like in the emergency department, I
almost never see a cycling woman with a
a heart attack, you know, activating the
Kath lab for them. The estradile is
protective. I'm not going to say it
never happens. There's always outliers
in medicine, but estradile is very
protective. Another reason why I mean in
your channel specifically too, those
they're justounding do not block
estradile, which is amazing. That needs
to be screamed from the rooftops forever
until everybody knows. But, you know, in
guys, it it's going to estradile helps,
you know, heart health, bone health,
erections, brain health. And so you
don't ever want to block it because in a
post-menopausal women once they
[clears throat] lose all their estrogen
now they have a much worse
cardiovascular risk. Now they're much
more prone to osteoporosis. You know
they get they can get vaginal atrophy
which turns into um they can get
recurrent urinary tract infections which
can be difficult to treat. All that is
prevented with hormones. You know,
sometimes I still need local vaginal
estrogen and I never want to if anybody
no woman should be denied vaginal
estrogen even if they've had cancer,
they smoke, anything like that because
um it helps restore those issues. I mean
vaginal estrogen even if you put it on
the back of your hand or your face helps
with r wrinkles and youthful appearance.
So, long story short, um, HRT for women
is extremely powerful and
[clears throat]
I I think almost all women benefit from
it and everybody like the WHI didn't
even touch on testosterone and in women
and women do incredibly well with
testosterone. I mean, obviously, it's
much more lower doses. it's controlled
and um they do so well in terms of you
know just executive function, their
confidence, their libido and so they do
really well with it. Um and that is
something that is very low in women as
well. just how we're seeing in guys,
younger and younger guys, women are
having almost undetectable
testosterone levels and even the ones
and then sometimes I know your channel
talks about SHBG as well. So SHBG will
bind up all the testosterone if they've
ever been on synthetic birth control
which a lot of women have. They can get
permanently high SHG and so even if
their testosterone is normal for a
female, it's still going to be
undetectable from a free testosterone
standpoint. And so a lot of these women
um do really well on testosterone
appropriately moni monitored
testosterone replacement and they don't
grow penises or grow beard or anything.
It just it helps them um
build their body better. It helps carry
their body better because they feel more
confident in themselves. And then now
they're starting to do more resistance
training. You know, I'm trying to get
we're trying to get women away from the
nothing tastes as good as skinny feels,
you know, and just eat as little as
possible, the special K diets. We we're
trying to push for the strong over
skinny woman, and that's going to
further help their muscle mass, their
bone mineral density. you know, they're
going to feel better. And then it will
hopefully help take some of that
psychological
>> fear away from just the number on the
scale because um you they can get more
muscle and be much more confident in
their body than if it was, you know,
they're just tiny trying to be as frail
as possible. So, um, all that to really
say is just HRT is very powerful in
women and [clears throat]
I hope it becomes more mainstream just
so women can really get the the benefits
they need from it.
>> Yeah. And maybe let's talk a little bit
more uh in a practical way for women. Uh
menopause is when estrogen crashes um
but much earlier um like testosterone
progesterone already starts to decline
rather early I guess 35 uh 40 uhish
already. So uh what's the first thing um
one should look for? Uh should we
measure uh progesterone regularly
starting from starting from 35 and uh
already um give a little bit of
progesterone early on.
>> Yeah, progesterone's progesterone is
magical in women and it is kind of all
over the place in a sense and I think
more and more women are getting just
[clears throat] essentially progesterone
deficient. You know, sometimes
progesterone is so impactful in women.
It's probably close to how testosterone
is in guys. You know, if the
progesterone's off, their cycles are
going to be off. They're they can have
more painful periods. They don't sleep
throughout the night. Their anxiety
worsens. And then a lot of female
ailments, PCOS, endometriosis, a lot of
that stuff can be improved with
progesterone. And so, but monitoring the
levels is kind of tough uh because you
know you have higher progesterone the
first half of the cycle then it goes
down and uh so it's kind of all over. So
you you if you want to be meticulous you
follow the progesterone levels and then
based off where they are in their cycle.
Um for the most part we use it just kind
of like how we do a lot of our hormone
replacement is just symptom management.
If they have symptoms of low
progesterone, uh difficulty sleeping,
period irregularities, um that kind of
stuff, then we'll bring on progesterone.
Um sometimes we cycle it, sometimes it's
continuous, depends on uh the individual
lady. And then menopause we are
typically keeping it on uh continuously
and [clears throat] we're not cycling
it, but we do cycle in some as well. Uh
but to kind of answer your question, uh
monitoring it has some utility, but
we'll will most likely just go off of
symptoms in regards to progesterone.
>> Agree. What's the best administration
route for progesterone?
>> I mean, we love the oral to purposely
get the first pass through the liver to
get the alopregnolone to help get the
GABA improvements in the brain. So, it
helps with sleep, it helps with anxiety
the next day. um you know sometimes they
need a little bit of extra and so you'll
want to avoid that specifically. There
are others like you know troies or tro
or vaginal progesterone that kind of
stuff to where they won't be as drowsy
if you need extra during the day and but
I would say for the vast majority we try
and purposely do oral to purposely get
the first pass effect um to purposely
get the drowsiness the tiredness and the
anxiety improvements from the alopin
alone from it.
>> So and they take that before bed I
guess.
>> Yep. Most time at night. Mhm. All right.
So, and then um okay, they they they
keep on taking the progesterone uh just
till the moment of uh the the menopause
and then the estrogen crashes. Uh what
what what's up next? Estrogen. What do
those what administration route?
>> Yeah. And it's kind of um yeah, estrogen
there at the try. It's hard to bring in
estrogen if they're still cycling, but
sometimes late permenopause, you got to
bring it in if especially if they just
are having all the signs of menopause.
And and menopause is such a spectrum for
a woman. You know, I have some who go
through menopause and they just almost
didn't even know that they stop cycling,
you know, and then I have others who
just have every symptom and they're
miserable. They're suffering. I mean,
even just joint pains, eye dryness, kind
of things you don't even think would be
from a menopausal transition can happen.
But that's kind of something we'll be
looking out for. Um, you know, oral
estradiol is good because it does have
another first pass effect through the
liver that kind of helps with these
fatty acid esters which are really good
for the heart. Um, transermal whether
it's through a cream or a patch are good
especially if they have anything from a
coagulability standpoint um that you're
worried about. I don't really worry
about oral estradile too much personally
from uh replacement but um medical
legally I still would use a patch or
some sort of transmal estradile if they
smoked or had some sort of coagulopathy
um just to make sure that's okay. Yeah,
we'll bring that in when we need to.
Sometimes permenop late late per
menopause if you bring it in too early
you're going to have they'll they'll
have unwanted [clears throat] symptoms
abnormal bleeding breast tenderness um
moodiness that kind of stuff. So it's
it's a it's a fine titration on trying
to uh when to bring it in postmenopause.
Easy peasy. They need it. They need the
bone protection. They need the
cardiovascular protection. It helps
their mood libido. It's kind of like um
you know I kind of think estradile is
kind of more of the anti-depressant uh
for them whereas pre progesterone is the
anti-anxiety
and so balancing those can really help
uh just overall mood stability on top of
all the other metabolic
uh improvements that it'll do.
>> Awesome. And um when should we think
about adding testosterone for women? Is
that also early premenopause? Yeah, that
can kind of be at any time.
>> Symptoms, what symptoms do they
experience? Uh
>> yeah, and it's the same as guys, you
know, low energy, low drive, low
motivation, brain fog, poor libido, poor
muscle gain, uh increased fat
deposition. Um just same symptom as
guys. And we will screen it whenever,
meaning we if they have uh low
testosterone symptoms, we'll bring it
on. you know, if they're on synthetic
birth control, we got to talk about um
maybe an alternative form. It is you
don't want them to get pregnant on
testosterone. So, that has to be uh in
your uh thought process as well on how
they're preventing pregnancy if they can
if they're still of childbearing age. Um
and so, yeah, we'll bring it on at any
time. And again, they do wonderful with
it. Um I do I would say they're not as
sensitive to it as guys. You know, guys
are just extremely sensitive to it. And
some women are extremely sensitive to
it. You know, PCOS is somewhat of an
androgen sensitivity, but um most of
them do very well and we will uh we'll
bring it on really at any time.
Post-menopausal, easy peasy. A lot of
times they just don't have any and again
it helps protect bones and helps you
know pmenopause with energy, libido
whenever they're struggling. And so, uh,
women of pretty much all adult women
could potentially benefit if they're low
and if, uh, they're symptomatic.
>> Yeah. And you, you also do this, uh, by
levels. Uh, you measure it first.
>> Yeah. We'll we'll measure it and see.
And same in guys, we'll we'll measure
total sex hormone binding globulin and
calculate their free. And women it's
kind of hard to really tell you like oh
you know in guys we can say 20 to 40 20
to 25 to 35 in a free testosterone in
guys and they typically do pretty well.
Women you know maybe two to four or so
but uh it's again just symptom based
wherever they feel the best is where
we'll do it. And some of them need a lot
lower and some of them will take a
little bit higher, you know, and so
we'll just uh kind of see again let
[clears throat] symptoms guide rather
than just the numbers on the on the
labs.
>> I guess premenopause it's very difficult
since they're still cycling um to to
recognize certain symptoms. They go on
and off and you have the three hormones
still cycling.
>> Yeah. And um you know testosterone you
know in a guy a young guy you put them
on testosterone and now we got to
address the fertility component [snorts]
in a in a female they still they still
cycle normally. You know as long as you
don't have these mega doses um and you
do it you know appropriately a lot of
times they still keep their normal
gonadotropins. they keep their normal
cycle and then they can kind of they can
get the benefits of the better energy
drive, motivation, libido, muscle
building, all that stuff without even
really uh impacting their cycle. And uh
and yeah, and then the last one is
thyroid. We all we're always going to be
optimizing thyroid in these women as
well. They're very they're s I feel like
they're more sensitive to thyroid than
guys are. And so along with all those
other ones, we're going to make sure
that they we can get their thyroid uh
dialed in where they can feel the best
with that. And then now they have just a
much better hormonal moo, you know, just
their overall mitochondria, body
chemistry just seems to all work
synergistically whenever all these are
uh circulating at decent levels.
In my practice as a dermatologist, I
hear more women than men over 50 state
and gaining weight. That that that's the
the hormone thing. Um what what hormone
causes this weight gain in women over
50?
>> Yeah, the estrogen decline kind of
changes where fat is deposited and so
getting their estrogen levels will help.
It is tough. I mean, I'll say guys just
cheat in terms of, you know, body
composition because I mean, I was just
comparing we get a a body scan uh for
muscle mass, body fat, visceral fat with
all of our patients. And I was just
comparing mine to the other nurse
practitioner and you know, my basil
metabolic rate is 2200 and hers is,00
you know, so I can eat double what she
can eat and not gain anything. where if
she eats what I eat, she's going to be
in a thousand calorie surplus, you know,
and so
>> they just have to be very mindful. And
that again is where the building muscle
comes in to give them a bigger metabolic
engine, you know, so that they can uh
you know, eat a little bit more and
everything, but it it comes they just
have to be extremely mindful because
they are um very sensitive to increased
fat deposition and everything. And I
mean, we see it all the time. These
women who have been active their whole
lives and then their estrogen stops
dropping and they do just um maintain.
They put on more than what they would
previously and they haven't changed too
much. They're still very active and
mindful, but the hormones just kind of
work against them. And so making sure
their thyroid and their testosterone
will are optimal will help with body
composition, just kind of overall
metabolism. and then uh estrogen,
progesterone just help them feel better
so that they will keep carrying things
out, you know, and so it's just kind of
but they it is it is a hard process for
for them and us, you know, they just got
to be meticulous and we'll try and get
the hormones right and then they'll have
to kind of take over from there in terms
of trying to get some resistance
training. Even it's just twice a week,
you know, it makes a difference in terms
of muscle mass, bone mineral density,
and overall body composition. But, you
know, I'm really main I'm really pushing
it more for bone mineral density, muscle
mass, their any muscle they can get in
their 50s, that's going to be their
longevity token to their 70s, their 80s,
their 90s, so that we can keep them
happy and functional and uh independent
in all those years.
>> Uh, is it your experience that men are
more open to or willing to work out
resistance train than than women? Yeah,
[snorts] it's just I think it just stems
especially uh women in their 60s plus,
they just have that mindset that they
need to be as frail or not frail,
they've turned frail, but they need to
be as skinny as possible, you know, and
guys, guys just want to we have that
drive. We want to lift and do more and
so it's a little easier to get a guy
doing it. But man, if you get a woman to
do it, they again they they just feel so
empowered. They um feel better. They're
more confident. And then you know you
get them resistance training and in the
ER very common thing uh is you know a
hip fracture in a woman uh just because
they get severe osteoporosis and you
know the resistance training is going to
prevent that fracture if they fall you
know but if they're doing stuff they may
even prevent the fall completely now
they have better muscle mass better
propriception and so you know just
prevents that uh fall from even
happening and don't even worry about it
but even if they do fall, they'll bounce
instead of breaking that hip. And the
hip fracture statistics are always so
profound. It's like 50% of those will
that break a hip will die within a year.
Um, and of those 50% that survive, 50%
of them will not get back to their level
of independence, you know. So that's
screams horrible morbidity
um associated with a hip fracture. And
so trying again trying to you know
backtrack look back 10 20 years what did
we need to do to prevent that day and
it's you know working on protein intake
resistance training hormone optimization
that kind of stuff. So yeah we we try to
quote unquote prescribe at least two
days of resistance training to anybody
that comes and sees us.
>> Yeah sure. again comparing women and
men. Um the administration route for
testosterone um I guess I don't know but
I would guess that women are um much
less uh wanting to um inject
testosterone than men. Is that right?
>> Yeah. You know really they with the GOPs
uh you know injecting yourself is kind
of and peptides you know injecting
yourself is not as scary as what they
think. And so we pro just like guys we
probably have more on injections than we
have cream. We have several in cream. Um
and like in guys I use uh cream as well
and I'll have them apply it to their
scrotum. Women uh I'll kind of have them
do the same external labia or inner
thigh you know sometimes they just don't
want to do external labia but inner
thigh and they kind of get the same like
guys applying it to their scrotum get
better DHT and so maybe it helps with
libido a little bit more. Um, but the
injections twice a week for women do
amazing. You know, they do a good job
and it's easy to adhere to for the most
part. Um, yeah, and they they they do
just fine. We don't have many that's
really against it at all that I was
expecting. I figured most of them would
be on cream, but most of I I'd say the
majority are probably on injections with
this.
>> Okay. I wouldn't have expected that.
>> Yeah.
Um
uh do you have uh couples coming in
together both for HRT?
>> Yeah, occasionally. And it kind of since
I was just guys at first it was just
guys uh but now they'll kind of come in
and we still try and separate them for
the most part just so that you know
they're not talk telling each other. You
know sometimes it's positive for them
but I still like to talk to whether it's
a man or a woman individually so that we
know the individual goals. But yeah, we
have several uh couples that are doing
it together and it works great. So we
don't mismatch their libido or anything,
which was one of the things that I kind
of struggled with with guys. Um,
whenever I was just a men's health only
clinic, you know, the guy feels great on
testosterone and his woman is beating
him or trying to keep him off with a
pole, you know. So, um, sometimes
helping the woman out, you know,
sometimes the woman out does the guy
now. And so, we kind of got to make
sure, uh, just balancing it is is the
goal between them. And
>> testosterone does a great job. Um, there
are a couple other things out there.
PT-141 is a peptide that we use for
women. It's kind of like on demand. I'd
say close to female Viagra
um that does pretty good. It has a brand
FDA brand name of Vilei. Um those
there's Philandin which is brand name
Addi and that kind of helps increase
just a baseline level desire. It's
expensive so we don't have tons on that
and haven't had tons of success but have
had some. Uh, and then you know like a
daily tadalapil for a guy. Women can get
a little bit of benefits from that.
Sometimes we'll do oxytocin and that
kind of helps um both men and women in
terms of sexual health. Um,
interesting. I had a guy um you've had
Nico on a uh here before, Nikico Mesla.
I've talked with him and he was using
oxytocin as a um like PTSD for guys and
using it for social anxiety and I uh uh
have a couple that do that and it works
well. Musician that sprays it before he
goes on. He's says it's great for PTSD.
Anyways, that's a little sidebar. I got
off on that. Um,
but yeah, women can have a little bit or
we have a little bit more of a sexual
health component, erectile dysfunction
as well that we can go further down,
especially if that's something that um
they want to talk about during their
appointment as well.
>> Yeah. Awesome. Um, are there certain
diet recommendations that you give both
to men and women um getting older?
>> Still, is it going to be protein? I
mean, if people listen to me or come in
and listen, I'm sure they get tired of
me talking about protein, but especially
as you get older, you just get, you
know, androgen resistance and, you know,
protein resistance. So, you actually
need even more protein to get this
response that we're trying to get out of
it. And so, um, I want both of them to
be trying to get a gram per pound of
goal body weight a day. And um you know
I fiber is undertalked about but I want
people to get fiber um to help you know
just regular bowel movement especially
if they're on a GLP-1. Um but it also
helps prevent colon cancer and a ton of
other cancer. So fiber needs to be on
there and sometimes the carnivore guys
are you know against that or whatever
but I think uh fiber still plays a very
important part you know through leafy
greens vegetables fruits you know
whatever their preference is but you
know from that stand I don't do t I
don't try and give them you know tons of
macros or anything I just like get your
protein in stay get a calorie goal you
know whether if we're trying to build
maintain or lose we kind of give them a
calorie goal
and then build that day that works for
you. Meaning be consistent with it. But
you got to be if you're tracking, you
got to know weigh out your liquids, your
dipping sauces, that kind of stuff. As
boring as that sounds, as meticulous as
that is, that's the backbone of knowing
where you stand. And so we try and get
them to track for a little bit just to
build calorie awareness. I don't I'm not
saying they have to do it forever, but
just so they know how many calories are
in their liquids, their dipping sauces,
everything it's coming from. And then um
aside from that, you know, their
protein, their calorie goal, and get
their protein, get some fiber in there.
And that's about the extent of my diet
to try and make it to where it's not too
complex. And then, uh we'll try and
build them a diet. You know, there's
tons of AI programs now that, you know,
just put in
how many calories you want in a day, how
much protein you want, how much fiber
you want, and what you like, what you're
allergic to, what, you know, if this
diet works for you. I mean, they'll spit
out a meal for you, you know, and keep
it under this budget, and they'll spit
it out for you. So, it's awesome. Um,
[clears throat] so utilize the tools we
have these days um to help make that um
Yeah, mainly protein as as they age is
just get the protein in because their
diet's going to go down. And protein
shakes are fine. They have a great amino
acid profile. They're absorbed well. You
know, just find one that doesn't tear up
your gut. Most of them taste much they
taste much better today than what they
did 15 years ago. You know, they used to
be so chalky you couldn't hardly even
stomach them. Now it's a dessert at the
end of a a meal. You know, they taste
great. So,
>> yeah. Agree. One last thing I wanted to
touch upon. Um I hear a lot of people,
men and women over 45, 50, complain
about uh joint pains. Typically they
tell me, "I would love to uh go to the
gym, but I can't. I have a tendon ache
here or joint pain in my hips or
whatever." What are your uh standard
recommendations for joint complaints
supplements and maybe also peptides? I
have no experience with peptides.
>> Yeah. And so there's a few. And again,
my my initial thing is is pretty boring
and it's [clears throat] and it's not
very sexy in terms of like wherever
you're hurting, I want you to try and
make sure that you strengthen above and
below the joint. You know, if it's a
knee, make sure your quads are strong,
anterior tibia strong. you know, if you
need formal physical therapy to give you
just a regimen so that you can
strengthen and make sure you have good
mobility around, you know, for backs,
you know, that you have good core, that
you're stretching, you know, and then I
don't want you to be scared to where
you're not doing things. You know,
[clears throat] people used to say, "Oh,
my back hurts, so here's a week of bed
rest." No, I want you to be up moving
what you can tolerate. You know, let the
pain guide you. Don't push through the
pain with any of this stuff, but you
know, get get a regimen where you stay
active, you move things, you you know,
grease the grease the gears and uh work
on your strength and mobility where you
can. And then you can add in, you know,
some of the supplements. Yeah. In terms
of joints, there's nothing that like,
ah, man, this do this and it's going to
clear it up. I mean like um glucosamine,
chondroitin, fish oil, uh the collagen
powders, that kind of stuff, hyaluronic
acid that they may have some utility and
you can take them. If they work for you,
great. Do them. Um I the growth hormone
secrets help with uh joint pain
sometimes. Uh it in the like growth
hormone guys, sometimes it can worsen
joint pain um if they're going way out.
You know, those aren't my uh population.
that with the growth home security
guards a lot of times I don't have
worsening joint planes typically it
helps them the one that everybody you
know these days is all the rage is BPC57
I like BPC um I think it has great use I
just again am not very sexy in terms of
I tell guys we don't have long-term
human studies just to say this is to
take freely willy-nilly
and I do think it has millions of good
anecdotes we just don't have the human
studies to say that it uh works or
doesn't, you know, or is safe or not. I
think it works well. I've had a lot of
good anecdotes myself with the patients
and they've had a lot of good results.
But, you know, the the big scary thing
that is a biologic pathway is it goes
through the VEF pathway to help promote
angogenesis which you know in a area of
pain, ligaments, joints, tendons that
don't have a lot of blood flow and
you're improving blood flow. um it helps
and that's where it, you know, helps
reduce the pain is improving blood flow.
If there's a cancer we didn't know
about, it could have made it more
aggressive. You know, has this been
really proved through the studies? Not
really, but it hasn't not been proved.
And so I'm just kind of, you know, I
have this conversation with them and
it's like, yeah, it sounds scary. It
could be there. Um I don't know if it's
there or not. It's just something that I
don't want to catch us by surprise in 10
years, you know, because you wanted to
get your joint pain [clears throat]
fixed in two weeks compared with four
weeks, you know. So, um again, that
sounds very um boring, but I I think it
is just worth of a conversation of
having with the data we have today.
Hopefully somebody picks it up, does
legitimate human studies, randomized
control trials, and we can um you know,
put that stuff to the side. That's just
today the knowledge I have. There's
like, I don't know, one or two human
studies that aren't randomized control
trials and everything is in rats. And in
rats and stuff, it looks awesome. I
mean, they'll sever their Achilles
tendon and it grows back and it's even
more structurally sound than what it was
prior. I mean, yeah, sounds awesome. Um
I just kind of let them know like ah you
know let's uh let's try you know make
sure physical therapy is first. We have
a you know a shockwave machine the extra
corporal shockwave machine that does
well. We'll do PRP injections. Um I
don't have an ultrasound so I won't do
it hip or back in office but other uh
joints that we'll do PRP and that has
good results. Um, and so but really at
the I if if it's something acute or I
want to make sure they went through
appropriate strengthening and stretching
prior before we're trying all the more
experimental stuff. Netra corporal stuff
and PRP has some literature but uh in
terms of like BPC and stuff I'm kind of
doing it as a if the other stuff has
failed we'll we'll bring it on and
you're okay with the unknown.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Agree. All right. So
uh thank you so much Mason for sharing
all this. If people would want to
contact you, how can they do that?
>> Yeah, we are in Texas and we can do
teley medicine throughout Texas. Uh
we're in St. Angelo, Texas specific if
you're happen to be local. Um and then
we're on all the socials. We're on
YouTube at Live Oak Health more longer
form content and then there's uh
Instagram, Facebook, Tik Tok at Live Oak
Testosterone. Awesome. [snorts]
Uh maybe any last advice to the people
still watching, men and women.
>> Yeah, I mean uh just nothing that comes
off to aside from just get moving. Find
something that you like to do. You know,
if you don't have an exercise regimen,
whether it's with friends, family, pets,
a competition, you know, just try and
find something that you look forward to
doing that you don't talk yourself out
of, you know, that you can do 30, 40
minutes a few times a week. And if you
can do it with people, humans are, you
know, we like to be around other people
and so a lot you'll adhere to it a lot
longer. And so just find something that
you like to do and move as much as you
can throughout the day.
>> Awesome. Thank you so much uh for this
nice talk, Mason. Thank you.
>> Yeah, thanks for having me on. That was
awesome.
Hey,
hey,
hey.